<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<?rfc strict="yes" ?>
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="4"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>
<rfc category="std" docName="draft-mmhbzm-intarea-udp-reflection-00"
     ipr="trust200902" updates="8335">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="UDP Reflection">User Datagram Protocol (UDP) Reflection</title>

    <author fullname="Sebastian Moeller" initials="S." surname="Moeller">
      <organization abbrev="">Organization</organization>

      <address>
        <email>moeller0@gmx.de</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Tal Mizrahi" initials="T." surname="Mizrahi">
      <organization abbrev="">Huawei</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Matam</street>

          <city>Haifa</city>

          <code>3190501</code>

          <country>Israel</country>
        </postal>

        <email>tal.mizrahi.phd@gmail.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Xiaoming He" initials="X." surname="He">
      <organization>China Telecom</organization>

      <address>
        <email>hexm4@chinatelecom.cn</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Tianran Zhou" initials="T." surname="Zhou">
      <organization abbrev="">Huawei</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>156 Beiqing Rd.</street>

          <city>Beijing</city>

          <code>100095</code>

          <country>China</country>
        </postal>

        <email>zhoutianran@huawei.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Ron Bonica" initials="R." surname="Bonica">
      <organization>Juniper Networks</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>

        <email>rbonica@juniper.net</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Xiao Min" initials="X." surname="Min">
      <organization>ZTE Corp.</organization>

      <address>
        <email>xiao.min2@zte.com.cn</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date year="2025"/>

    <workgroup>Network</workgroup>

    <keyword>UDP</keyword>

    <abstract>
      <t>
      This document describes the UDP Reflection utility. It is similar to Ping 
      in that it relies on a stateless message exchange between two hosts. 
      The initiating host sends a UDP packet with an unused destination port
      and the destination host sends back an ICMP Destination Unreachable.
      The payload of the ICMP message includes a possibly trimmed copy of the
      original UDP message. Specifically, if the original message is sent 
      over IPv6, the ICMP message includes the IPv6 header and IPv6 extension 
      headers and options if they are present. 
      </t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction">
      <t>The UDP Reflection utility is a UDP <xref target="RFC768"/> based
      diagnostic tool. It is similar to the Ping <xref target="RFC2151"/> 
      utility as it uses a message exchange between an initiating host and
      a destination host.</t> 

      <t>Each message exchange includes:</t> 
      <t><list style="symbols">
          <t>A UDP packet that is sent by the initiating host to the 
          destination host with a reserved destination port number.
          Port 33434 has been reserved by IANA for Traceroute and is
          used in UDP Reflection as well.</t>

          <t>An ICMP Destination Unreachable that is sent back to the
          initiating host due to the unused port in the UDP packet. The
          ICMP message includes, in its payload, the original UDP packet
          (or a trimmed version of it), including its IP header and
          payload.</t>
        </list></t>

      <t>UDP Reflection operates in a similar manner to the last hop of 
      the Traceroute utility <xref target="RFC2151"/>. As opposed to 
      Traceroute, UDP Reflection does not iteratively try to reach each
      of the routers along the path to the destination, but directly
      sends a UDP packet to the destination host.</t>

      <t>The UDP Reflection exchange allows the initiating host to
      verify the reachability to the destination and to measure the round-trip
      time. The initiating host can also extract the header of the original
      packet from the received ICMP message, allowing to analyze header
      fields or extension headers that were modified along the path
      between the initiating host and the destination host.</t>

    </section>

    <section title="Requirement Language">
        <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
        "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "NOT RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and
        "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as described in BCP
        14 <xref target="RFC2119"/> <xref target="RFC8174"/> when, and only
        when, they appear in all capitals, as shown here.</t>
    </section>


    <section anchor="UseCaseSec" title="Use Cases">
      <t>The following protocols define mutable IPv6 extension headers that can be
      used to trace a path and its performance:</t>

      <t><list style="symbols">
          <t>IPv6 Options for In Situ Operations, Administration, and
          Maintenance (IOAM) <xref target="RFC9486"/></t>

          <t>Inband Flow Analyzer <xref target="I-D.kumar-ippm-ifa"/></t>

          <t>Path Tracing in SRv6 networks <xref
          target="I-D.filsfils-ippm-path-tracing"/></t>

          <t>Segment Routing Header encapsulation for In-situ OAM Data <xref
          target="I-D.ali-spring-ioam-srv6"/></t>
        </list></t>

      <t>These extensions are used to collect information along a packet's
      delivery path. Currently, the collected information is sent to a
      controller for processing. However, in some cases this information is
      relevant to the sender.</t>

      <t>The Reflection utility defined in this document provides a mechanism by which this
      information can be returned to the initiating host.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="TheorySec" title="Theory of Operation">
      <t>The UDP Reflection utility is invoked by an initiating host that sends
      a sequence of one or more packets. Each message exchange includes the
      following procedure:</t>

      <t><list style="symbols">
          <t>The initiating host sends a UDP packet with a reserved UDP 
          destination port. Port 33434, which has been reserved by IANA for 
          Traceroute, is used for this purpose. The packet can be sent
          over IPv4 or IPv6. If the packet is IPv6, it can include one
          or more extension fields.</t>

          <t>The destination host receives the UDP packet and detects that
          the UDP destination port is unused. It generates an ICMP Destination
          Unreachable back to the initiating host. If the original packet
          is IPv4, then the ICMP message includes the first 8 octets of 
          the original packet, as defined in <xref target="RFC792"/>. If
          the original packet is IPv6, the ICMP message includes as much
          of the original message as possible without exceeding the MTU,
          as defined in <xref target="RFC4443"/>.</t>

          <t>The initiating host receives the ICMP message and can analyze
          its payload.</t>
        </list></t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="IANA" title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>This document does not include any requirements from IANA.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Security" title="Security Considerations">
      <t>From a security perspective this document does not introduce new 
      security threats beyond the threats that are already applicable for 
      existing ICMP messages, and are described in <xref target="RFC792"/> 
      and <xref target="RFC4443"/>.</t>
    </section>
  
  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.2119'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.8174'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.768'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.792'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.4443'?>
    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">
      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.9486'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.filsfils-ippm-path-tracing'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.ali-spring-ioam-srv6'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.kumar-ippm-ifa'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.2151'?>

    </references>

	</back>
</rfc>
